A Guide to the Varner Family Papers, 1804-1933: SC 3035
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Varner Family Papers,
1804-1933
Special Collections, James Madison University
Varner Family
SC 0129
.4 cubic feet; 1 box
The Varner Family Papers, 1804-1933, documents the Varner family of Page County, Virginia with particular emphasis on correspondence, legal and financial documents, and documents relating to their distillery business.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
This collection is on deposit from the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society.
Bio/Historical Note
The Varner family of Page County, Virginia was of German descent, and their name appears as early as 1801 on records of the Antioch Christian Church near Stony Man Creek, Virginia.
Despite wide-spread anti-liquor sentiment in the Shenandoah Valley in the nineteenth century, the Varners operated a distillery. Documentary evidence of the business begins in 1869 and includes state permits to distill, Internal Revenue "Distillery Gauger" forms, and several orders for brandy.
Scope and Content
The Varner Family Papers, 1804-1933, document the Varner family of Page County, Virginia with particular emphasis on correspondence, legal and financial documents, and documents relating to their distillery business.
Series 1: Letters, 1816-1910, contains documents from relatives of the Varners in the Midwest and from other family members within Virginia. Most of these documents date from the latter half of the nineteenth century. In general these letters discuss health, the weather and farming; however, there are several accounts relating to the Civil War and its devastating effects on the family.
Series 2: Legal Documents, 1804-1931, contains a thorough collection of tax receipts dating from 1803-1930; several papers pertaining to John Varner's duties as an executor; a folder of receipts for various financial transactions; and, among other papers in the miscellaneous folder, a Confederate States of America Bond.
Series 3: Distillery Papers, 1869-1893, contains documents related to the Varner's distillery business in Luray, Virginia. Despite wide-spread anti-liquor sentiment in the Shenandoah Valley in the nineteenth century, the Varners operated a distillery. Documentary evidence of the business begins in 1869 and includes state permits to distill, Internal Revenue "Distillery Gauger" forms and several orders for brandy.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series:
Series 1: Letters, 1816-1933
Series 2: Legal Documents, 1804-1931
Series 3: Distillery Papers, 1869-1893
Bibliography
Lambert, Darwin S. The Undying Past of Shenandoah National Park. Boulder, CO: Roberts Rinehart, Inc., 1989.
Strickler, Harry M. A Short History of Page County Virginia. Richmond, VA: Dietz Press, Inc., 1952.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Varner family; Varner family -- Correspondence; Varner, John; Agriculture -- Virginia -- History -- 19th century; Distilleries -- Virginia -- Sources; Liquor laws -- Virginia; Liquor -- Selling; Financial statements -- Virginia; Estates (Law) -- Virginia -- Sources; Page County (Va.) -- History -- Sources; Virginia -- Sources; Page County (Va.) -- Social life and customs -- Sources; Page County (Va.) -- Economic conditions -- Sources; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History -- Sources; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- Social life and customs -- Sources; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- Economic conditions -- Sources; Virginia -- History, Local -- Sources; Virginia -- Social life and customs -- Sources; Virginia -- Economic conditions -- Sources; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives, Confederate; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Destruction and pillage
- Series 1: Letters, 1816-1933
  - Letters from Virginia, 1816-1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Virginia, 1866-1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters from the Midwest, 1840-1869 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters from the Midwest, 1870-1910, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series 2: Legal Documents, 1804-1931
  - Tax Receipts, 1804-1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Executor Documents, 1822-1836 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Financial Documents, 1807-1931, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Documents, 1823-1910 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series 3: Distillery Papers, 1869-1893
  - Distillery Papers, 1869-1893 (Box 1, Folder 9)